Register of the Bertha June Richardson Lucas papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Bertha June Richardson Lucas papers
1901-1945
45007
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
The Bertha June Richardson Lucas papers consist of the correspondence, writings, and notes of June Richardson Lucas relating to relief work in World War I and politics and international relations in the 1930s. Also included in the collection are numerous pamphlets, newspapers, and clippings from various countries, dating from the 1930s.
Lucas, Bertha June Richardson.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1945.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1878 June 6 Born in Indianapolis, Indiana
1901 Educated at Smith College, Massachusetts
1901-1902 Taught Biology at Central High School in Cleveland, Ohio
1902-1903 Studied Biology and Economy at Barnard College, New York
1903-1904 Was Barnard's Mary Lowell Stone Fellow
1904 Published economic book, The Woman Who Spends
1904-1905 Worked as a writer and lecturer in New York
1905-1909 Taught History at Brearley School, New York
1909 November 8 Married Dr. William Palmer Lucas in Deerfield, Massachusetts Moved to Boston, Massachusetts
1914 Moved to San Francisco, California
1917 July 14 Sailed to Europe to work for the Red Cross in Switzerland and France
1917-1919 Served as the Director of Foreign Publicity for the American Red Cross
1918 Published The Children of France and The Red Cross Returned to the United States and worked for the Red Cross in Washington, D.C.
1928 Worked for Herbert Hoover's Presidential Campaign
1929 Served as Chairmen of the Budget Committee for character-building organizations in San Francisco, California
1936 November Served on the Executive Committee of the Round Table Leaders and Lecturers for the Institute of International Relations at Mills College, California
1937 May Served as Chairman of the San Francisco Emergency Peace Campaign Committee
1937 June Was Hostess in charge of the Round Table at the Friends' International Institution at Mills College
1937 September- 1938 June Travelled abroad to Geneva, Switzerland; London, England; and Dublin, Ireland
1938-1940 Gave lectures on international affairs in Europe and the United States
1939 Was a lecturer for the San Francisco Classroom Teacher's Association Served as a member of the Research and Budget Committee of the San Francisco Community Chest
1939 November Served as Chairman of the Program for Peace Projects at the San Francisco Fair, and as Chairman of preparations for the West Coast Conference of Pan-Pacific Women's Association
1940 January-March Taught "International Life" course to San Francisco's League of Women
1940 February Served as Vice President of Peace Projects, Inc.
1940 June Presided over informal forums after opening lectures at the History of International Relations at Mills College
1942 June Received honorary M.A. from Mills College Organized General Noble Center for men in service
1943 Served as Regional Chairman of National Group of Pan Pacific Woman's Assembly
1944 Served as Chairman of the Commission for Ministry to US Forces Service Personnel
Scope and Content of Collection
The Bertha June Richardson Lucas papers consist of the correspondence, writings, lectures and notes of June Richardson Lucas, and pamphlets, newspapers, and clippings from the 1930s. Most of the material relates to relief work in World War I, international relations and peace efforts in the 1930s, British and Irish politics and relations, and community and women’s groups in the United States.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 14 series: Biographical File; Correspondence; Speeches and Writings; Memoranda; Minutes; Notes; Course and Reading Lists; American Association of University Women; Lectures; Printed Matter; Maps; Photographs; Poems; and Miscellany.
Great Britain--Politics and government--20th century.; International relief.; Ireland--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--1933-1945.; World politics.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.
- Biographical File, 1937-1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence, 1925-1943 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Speeches and Writings, 1901-1940
  - Articles, 1901-1939 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Lectures, 1921-1940
    - The Now in World Affairs, 1929 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - People and Places, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 5)
      - 1938 (Box-folder 1: 5)
      - 1938 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - for City Club, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Current Affairs and their World Backgrounds, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - General, 1921-1940 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - 1921-1928 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - 1929-1936 (Box-folder 1: 10)
      - 1937-1940 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Partial Drafts, 1930-1940 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Pamphlets, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Poems, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 14)
- Memoranda, 1934 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Minutes, 1930-1938
  - American Council Institute of Pacific Relations, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Council of League of Nations, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Notes, 1925-1942
  - 1925-1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1925-1942 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 1925-1942 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Course and Reading Lists, 1925-1935 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- American Association of University Women file, 1924-1936 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Lectures, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Printed Matter, 1917-1943
  - Programs, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Pamphlets, 1921-1942 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Leaflets, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Government Publications, 1922-1938 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Serial Issues, 1917-1938
    - Bulletins, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Newspapers, 1937-1938
      - British Newspapers, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 3: 2)
        - 1937 (Box-folder 3: 2)
        - 1938 (Box-folder 3: 3)
        - 1938 (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - Irish Newspapers, 1937-1938
        - 1937 (Box-folder 3: 5)
        - 1938 (Box-folder 3: 6)
        - 1938 (Box-folder 3: 7)
      - Panamanian Newspapers, 1937 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Clippings, 1918-1943
    - General, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - British, 1937-1938
      - Politics and Government, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 2)
      - Military, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 3)
      - Foreign Relations, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - British and Irish Relations, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Egypt, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - European Politics, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - India, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Irish, 1937-1943
      - Politics and Government, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Foreign Relations, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 4: 10)
      - Social Conditions, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Germany, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Palestine, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Soviet Union, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - United States, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Arts and Entertainment, 1918-1938 (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - Health, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - History, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - Religion, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Science and Education, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - Society, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - Women, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 22)
- Maps, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 4: 23)
- Photographs, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 24)
- Poems, 1937 (Box-folder 4: 25)
- Miscellany, 1930-1938 (Box-folder 4: 26)